<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hyrelings reward: or, a serious word to considering people. Being a relation of some difference between Mr. William Jenkyns, and some others. Occasioned by the questioning of his doctrin, and his undertaking to defend it; together with his argument, by which he pretended to do it. As also his reasons of deserting his undertaking; with an answer to his said argument and reasons; together with some queries touching the point in question; with the manner of his being publiquely opposed, and the deportment of himself and his people thereupon: / all faithfully laid down by R.T.</title>
            <author>R. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T46</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E655_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205951</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865167</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865167</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166061</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95541)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166061)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 100:E655[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hyrelings reward: or, a serious word to considering people. Being a relation of some difference between Mr. William Jenkyns, and some others. Occasioned by the questioning of his doctrin, and his undertaking to defend it; together with his argument, by which he pretended to do it. As also his reasons of deserting his undertaking; with an answer to his said argument and reasons; together with some queries touching the point in question; with the manner of his being publiquely opposed, and the deportment of himself and his people thereupon: / all faithfully laid down by R.T.</title>
                  <author>R. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. and T.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "21 February 1651".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166061:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HYRELINGS REWARD: <hi>OR,</hi> A ſerious Word to conſidering People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BEING</hi> A RELATION Of ſome Difference between Mr. WILLIAM JENKYNS, and ſome Others.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned by the Queſtioning of his <hi>Doctrin,</hi> and his undertaking to defend it; Together with his Argument, by which he pretended to do it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo</hi> His <hi>Reaſons</hi> of deſerting his undertaking; With an
<hi>Anſwer</hi> to his ſaid <hi>Argument</hi> and <hi>Reaſons;</hi> Together with ſome Queries touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Point in Queſtion; with the manner of his being pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely oppoſed, and the Deportment of himſelf and his people thereupon: All faithfully laid down by <hi>R. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Study to ſhew thy ſelf approved, one that need not be aſhamed, rightly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the Word of Truth.</p>
               <bibl>2 Tim. 2. 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>But he anſwered and ſaid, Every plant which my heavenly Father hath not planted, ſhall be rooted up.</p>
               <bibl>Matt. 15. 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The Hyreling fleeth, and careth not for his ſheep, becauſe he is a Hyreling.</p>
               <bibl>Joh. 10. 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> and <hi>T. W.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:166061:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:166061:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Poſſibly thou mayſt have taken up the obſervation before me, but however it will not be amiſſe to remind thee of it, <hi>viz.</hi> That a perſon full of prejudicate thoughts, and prepoſſeſt with ſtrong pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt either perſons, or things, doctrines or opinions, lyes under a very great diſadvantage, and ſtands upon terms of the greateſt improbability that likely can be, to ſee far, or to ſearch deep into the <hi>myſteries</hi> of Truth; yea, the truth is, that one great reaſon why men abide ſo long in the <hi>Earth,</hi> and do not mount up into the <hi>Heavens</hi> themſelves; I mean why they converſe no more with thoſe great and excel'ent things which are preſented to the view of men in the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt; why they ſolace and delight themſelves no more with <hi>viſions of life and immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> but are ſuch ſtrangers unto the glory of <hi>ſpiritual</hi> imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; it is becauſe they are already wedded unto ſomething or other, either in their
<hi>judgements</hi> (or rather <hi>wills)</hi> or <hi>practiſes,</hi> or both, which to them is as a beloved <hi>Dallilah,</hi> which whoſoever riſeth up to oppoſe, or queſtion (although it be onely to ſearch into the grounds thereof, and ſo if it be a <hi>Truth,</hi> to eſtabliſh them the more firmly therein; if <hi>Errour,</hi> to ſhew them that it cannot bleſs them) ſhall notwithſtanding be the hatred of their ſouls; they are already prepoſſeſt with hard thoughts againſt the perſons, and prejudice againſt ſuch doctrines or opinions, whereof the ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the one, and the tendency of the other ſhall be to unſettle or take them off the Lees of their preſent imbrac'd opinions, although it be to eſtabliſh them upon that <hi>Rock that is higher then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs,</hi> the clear path-way whereunto as yet they have not known, or at leaſt have not been ſo well acquainted with: It is a common ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but I judge it hath ſomewhat of weight in it, That <hi>Cuſtome.
<pb facs="tcp:166061:3"/> becomes a ſecond nature;</hi> Implying, that whatſoever men ſhall for a long time have <hi>accuſtomed</hi> themſelves unto, whether it be the owning and maintaining of any doctrine or opinion, or whether it be the practiſing of what they ſo own and maintain, or whatever elſe, their long accuſtomedneſs thereunto, renders it a matter very hard and difficult for any man whoſoever to remove them off their ſtanding herein, yea though their feet all this while have been ſet in ſlippery places, and he that deſires to remove them, doth it onely in order to this great deſigne, <hi>viz.</hi> That they might now ſtand in everlaſting felicity; yet nevertheleſs, the tranſplantation in this kind becomes (comparatively) as difficult, and almoſt as hard as the changing of Nature it ſelf, or the turning her out of her courſe; And upon this account, I ſuppoſe it is that the Spirit of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>himſelf ſpeaketh thus, <hi>Can the Blackmoore change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots?</hi> What then? Why then indeed <hi>may you that are accuſtomed to do evill, learn to do well:</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, that their long accuſtomedneſs unto evill, was that which now had made their
<hi>Learning to do well,</hi> ſo difficult and hard unto them.</p>
            <p>This ſuppoſed, and taken along with us, I conceive thou wilt not much w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder at the manner of the carriage of the buſineſs now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to thy view; Otherwiſe indeed it would ſeem very ſtrange, to ſee a man who owns himſelf as <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel</hi> (who of all others ought to apply himſelf ſo to the minds and conſciences of men, as (if poſſible) to convince all gain-ſayers; but however to be ready <hi>to give to every one that asketh him, a reaſon of that faith and hope that is in him,</hi> to ſee or hear ſuch a man deliver ſuch things for and under the name of Truths of God, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he refuſed to vindicate and maintain againſt gain-ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; yea, a reaſon, or account whereof he refuſed to give, though publikely deſired; denying alſo, to anſwer the Objections of his gain-ſayer; I ſuppoſe thou wilt readily reſolve this practice of his, <hi>[Mr.</hi> Jenkins] into that principle before-mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> A pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſedneſs of mind, and prejudicate opinion, either of the perſon or doctrine, or both, which now oppoſed him, being wedded, and deeply baptized into the Spirit of his own opinion, But (as there is too much cauſe to ſuſpect) upon much the ſame terms, as they that
<pb facs="tcp:166061:3"/> are repreſented by the ſtony ground in our Saviours parable, <hi>Matt. 13.
20.</hi> is ſaid to have received the Word, <hi>viz.</hi> (not having much root in themſelves) was therefore unwilling to have his Doctrine in this kinds too much ſearched into, or the ſpirit of it too far taſted by men, leaſt when the Truth of the Goſpel in this reſpect ſhould be brought forth into the light, the glory of this his opinion ſhould thereby be laid in the duſt:</p>
            <p>My humble requeſt therefore unto thee <hi>(Chriſtian Reader)</hi> is, That ſeeing ſuch a Rock before thee, thou wouldeſt be very eir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect and carefull, leaſt thou thy ſelf ſhouldeſt run upon it, and be ſplit in pieces by it; Know this, that Truth is no farther thine, then it is received by thee upon rational grounds; neither can it do thee any ſervice like it ſelf, till it firſt enters into thy ſoul by the door of thy underſtanding, and thence paſſes into thy judgement, and ſo proceeds into thy will and affection, and ſo comes forth into practice in thy life and converſation; And it is never like thus to enter (at leaſt not ſtrongly to poſſeſs thy judgment and conſcience) unleſs thou ſhalt be willing to weigh, and pounder, and look round about thee, and conſider on what account thou haſt or doſt receive it; Take therefore the Apoſtles councel, <hi>Try all things;</hi> ſift them to the Bran, ſearch them to the bottome, try them throughly, and then <hi>Hold faſt that which is good:</hi> Thou art never like to <hi>Hold faſt</hi> that which is good, unleſs thou ſhalt be willing and induſtrious to dive into the depth of the grounds, and reaſons of it, and to ſee the ſtrength that is in it, That thou mayſt be able thus to do in the Controverſie now before thee, ſhall be my prayer unto the God of Grace and Love, into whoſe boſome I now commend thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:166061:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166061:4"/>
            <head>The Hirelings Reward.</head>
            <p>IF it was as a Crown of glory and matter of exceeding joy and peace to the conſciences of the Apoſtles, in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing the malice and rage of the people, for and in their declaring and making known the counſels of God unto the world, and that they were accounted worthy to ſuffer ſhame and reproach from a malicious and perverſe generation, in the doing of ſuch a pice of ſervice as this was; and therefore they ceaſed not, but daily, and in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place endeavoured to finiſh their courſe; and their great deſign in this, was, That they might manifeſt the great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit they had in being one with Chriſt, that they alſo might<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 40, 41, 42.</note> have fellowſhip with him: And ſo the Apoſtle
<hi>Paul</hi> became all things to all, that he might gain ſome; and thus did he endeavour for the Goſpel ſake, that they might be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers therein with him, that is, that thereby the Goſpel might get ground upon the lives &amp; conſciences of men, and be more highly eſteemed by them, and thereby God would be honoured, the Apoſtles ſatisfied to ſee the fruits of their labours, and the world benefited; and doubtleſs the hearts of the Apoſtles were mightily born up in the managing of this great work by the words of their Lord and Maſter, that before had told them what they muſt expect, if they would undertake that piece of ſervice, how that they ſhould meet with abundance of perſecution and contradiction of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſhould be hated of all men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 22, 23. (that is of the moſt part of men) for his names ſake, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 20, 21. but with all comforts them with this conſideration, <hi>The
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166061:5"/> ſervant is not greater then his Maſter, Job.</hi> 30. 16. And if they have dealt ſo unworthily with him, they muſt expect to have a taſte of the ſame cup, 1
<hi>Pet.</hi> 1, 2. therefore he is ſaid in his ſuffering, to leave us that for an example, and we to follow his ſteps therein.</p>
            <p>I am now to preſent to thy view, that which is a trouble to my ſpirit, to conſider that I ſhould be ſo neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by unreaſonable men, that upon Chriſtian-like and honourable terms might have prevented the ſame, I ſhall as briefly as poſſibly I can give you a narration thereof. 1. I ſhall give you the occaſion, 2. the matter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the occaſion was this; On the fourth day of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> Mr. <hi>William Jenkins</hi> in his morning Lecture, preaching out of <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. 3. the words are theſe,
<hi>Becauſe of the ſavour of thy good Oyntment, thy Name is as Oyntment powred forth, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do the Virgins love thee:</hi> From the words Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> was pleaſed to raiſe theſe foure or five conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That Jeſus Chriſt he is a prevailing ſavour.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That he was an attractive and drawing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that he was a defuſive and ſpreading ſavour.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, he was an everlaſting and effecting ſavour, and where the ſcent of the ſavour was received, it could never be loſt.</p>
            <p>Preſently he ſaid, he had been in ſome places that were as the ſuburbs of Hell, where there was curſing, and ſwearing, and lying, &amp;c. and the reaſon of this was, becauſe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Chriſt was not there. And again, I have been in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, as have been as the Suburbs of Heaven, where their good counſel, and godly ſorrow and mourning for ſin; and the reaſon of this was, becauſe the ſavour of Chriſt was there: Now that which was taken notice of from theſe expreſſions, was this, Whereas he was pleaſed to ſay, The ſavour of Chriſt was a defuſive and ſpreading ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, ſpreading it ſelf in every place, and where it comes, it can never be loſt, and yet Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> had been in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where the ſavour was not, which is a meer contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:166061:5"/> ſo I with another went to him to his houſe, to ſee how he would reconcile theſe extreames: And when we had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that to him, which we averred to be a contradiction and untruth, he replyed; That he was ſure, there were none that uſed to hear him, but knew well enough what he meant; but more of this by and by: Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> was then pleaſed to ſay, That he did not ſay, <hi>The ſavour came in every place:</hi> but <hi>in every place that it came, it was received:</hi> If one man in a place received it, it was received in that place; and where it was received, it could never be left: For, ſaith he, this I am able to prove, if I ſhould undertake, that Chriſt was never preached in any place, but there was ſome one Perſon or more received it; But this I muſt tell Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> that it would be more eaſie for him to eate his words in this thing (as well as in others) than to prove, there was any one Perſon in <hi>Choraſin,</hi> with divers other Places, which might be mentioned: where Chriſt did moſt of his works, and yet not a word of any one Convert in them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was as much miſtaken in this, as in the reſt; But I hope I ſhall rule my Pen better then Mr.
<hi>Jenkins</hi> and Mr. <hi>Vicars,</hi> that were there preſent, ruled their tongues, I ſhould make the Reader bluſh to hear unſavoury and hard ſpeeches were received from them, and not onely againſt our ſelves, but others alſo that we thought not of, which onely trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled us; but enough of this; all the water we had could not queuch that flame of wrath and indignation that brake forth: but we have not ſo learned Chriſt to bring <hi>rayling for rayling;</hi> but rather <hi>with meekneſs inſtruct</hi> thoſe that oppoſe them; 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 24, 25. And ſuch as have taken that Office upon them, on whom this duty is enjoyned (but onely they have forgotten) and ſo in ſtead of inſtructing meekly, there is nothing but throwing dirt in mens faces; ſurely this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion commeth not of him that called him. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 8. When Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> did perceive what contradiction there was in his Poſitions, he was pleaſed to ſay, <hi>This was my ſenſe of it,</hi> (though before it was in a mentual reſervation) but we are not in ſuch caſes to take mens meanings, but their ſayings:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166061:6"/> then we came to ſpeak of the permanency, laſting and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualitie of the Savour of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But by the way I ſhall inform thee of one rarity in M. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> which is infallibility, indeed it was not onely new, but ſtrange to me; The occaſion of this ſaying in our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was, Mr. <hi>Vicars</hi> with hot indignation riſeth up from his ſeat, and ſaid, Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> you muſt take that courſe as formerly godly Orthodox men did, when they confer'd with Lay-men, to take their words in writing, leaſt they ſhould eat them: To which I replyed, That if Mr. <hi>Vicars</hi> were ſo well acquainted with Anthors, he muſt needs be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this alſo, that thoſe he calls Orthodox men, are ſubject to failings and miſtakes as well as others, elſe what meanes, or from whence cometh that contrariety of judgement, contradiction, grudging, and evil ſurmiſing, that every day appears in and amongſt them; therefore you may be ſilent therein: To which Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> replieth, I am infallable: I pray, ſaid I, demonſtrate that: I will, ſaith he, thus; <hi>God cannot lye,</hi> in this I am infalible: If this would prove him infalible, it wil prove all men infalible, for what man is there that doth acknowledge a God, but will ſay that his God is true; but how this will prove Mr. <hi>Jenkin's</hi> infallibility is beyond my underſtanding to conceive: If I ſay it is day, becauſe the Sun is in the Horizon, this thing is true, therefore I am infallible; but if I had ſaid ſo, Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> would have cried out blaſphemy; but that the ſpeaking of a truth cauſeth him that ſpeaketh it to be infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, I deny; for example, He that is called the Father of lyes ſaid, that Jeſus Chriſt was the Son of God,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 29. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 44. but this doth not prove him to be infalible, though what he ſpake was as true as that ſpake was as true as that ſpoken by Mr. <hi>Jenkins;</hi> ſo that it is evident, that the ſpeaking of a thing that is true, maketh not him that ſpeaketh it, infalible: To come to the Apoſtles themſelves, if any were infalible, they were (miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take me not) I do not deny, but abundantly acknowledge that they ſpake truth as the Spirit gave them utterance, but that they themſelves, their perſons, as compound of fleſh and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166061:6"/> bloud were unerring, is that which the Scripture no where to my remembrance teacheth: But on the contrary, <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf did thoſe things he allowed not,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 14, 15. And ſo the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>In ſome things we offend all:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is nothing in Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> Argument that doth in the leaſt degree prove his infalibility: If he had ſaid, God cannot lie, therefore he is infalible, I muſt have laid my hand upon my mouth and conſented to that: But that God that ſaith he cannot lye, ſaith, All men are lyars, <hi>Num. 23. 19. Rom.</hi> 3. 4. Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> is a man, therefore where is Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> infallibility.</p>
            <p>And when he had (as he thought) proved his unerring condition, then he laid down an Argument to prove his Doctrine to be ſo too (to wit) that thoſe that have once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſavour of Chriſt, can never loſe it; thus; That O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that contradicts that portion of Scripture which ſaith, He that beleeveth ſhall be ſaved, is an erroneous opinion.</p>
            <p>But that Doctrine that teacheth; a man may loſe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Chriſt, or fall from believing, is ſuch a Doctrine: Therefore, this Argument ſhall after be conſidered; when Mr.
<hi>Jenkins</hi> had laid down this Syllogiſme, he triumphed, as though he had called Heaven and earth to witneſs the ſame, and ſo departed as one that is ſent of a Meſſage, goeth away, who hath no anſwer thereunto, but taketh it in ſcorn that ſuch young men ſhould attempt ſuch a Royall Fort as he is, though Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> could ſay when he had to do with his ſeniors, that truth was their ſenior; ſo now it might have been ſaid to him (though by infancy) that truth was his elder: But Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> inſtead of explaining his termes and receiving an anſwer to what he propounded, challenged any of Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> members, or Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> himſelf, or all the world, to make his Argument good. We anſwered, we doubted not but to bring thoſe that ſhould manage the Controverſie, againſt you, but withall ſaid, we fear when any ſhall come to reaſon with you, the heat of your paſſion it is ſuch, that it will not ſuffer you to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166061:7"/> when followed cloſe, and cauſed to ſpeak to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; ſo we took our leave of him, and Mr. <hi>Bickerſtaffe</hi> that was then preſent, coming out with us, ſaid, You ſee now he hath challenged you, or any of you to diſpute the point; And thereupon we gave notice to ſome of Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> Congregation, how they were challenged, and likewiſe told them the occaſion, and ſome of them deſired me to give Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> notice, that they had accepted of his challenge, and would deſire him, that he would be pleaſed to appoint a time and place, that they might attend him, which I did accordingly, and told him that there would ſome anſwer his challenge: Challenge, ſaith he, you lye, I made no challenge with any, neither wil I diſpute with any of them: This was his anſwer, ſuch a one as I have not found in the mouth of any of the Watchmen of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> unleſs it was their own to deceive, <hi>Mica. 2. 11. Jer. 27. 10, 15. Jer. 28. 15. Ezek.</hi> 21. 29. But this makes me much admire, that Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bickerſtaffe</hi> ſhould both eat their words; the truth is, what the one ſaith, the other will not gainſay; So I told Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> I hoped, notwithſtanding he had ſo far forgot himſelf in his indignation and wrath, yet that he would undertake to prove his Doctrin, or give a reaſon to the contrary: And he gave three Reaſons, though I give them not to you in order, yet theſe are they, I will lay them down, and then leave the impartiall Reader to judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will excuſe him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſaith he, the truth is, I am higher then they, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Miniſter of the Goſpel, ought not to ſtoop or conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, or diſpute with ſuch men, this is one of them that wil bear him out againſt his engagement; And this he draweth from his Miniſterial Function as an Officer, or elſe as acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated with humane Learning and external parts, both which ſhall be conſidered; As for the firſt:</p>
            <p>1. Whether his Miniſterial Office doth give him this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, I am altogether ignorant thereof; And ignorant ſhall be ſtill, unleſs I could be perſwad all he was infallible; for no place of Scripture could he ſhew for it: If I am not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166061:7"/> miſtaken, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 24, 25. teacheth another leſſon, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord muſt not ſtrive; what then? <hi>be gentle,</hi> to whom? <hi>to all men,</hi> as if he had ſaid, Men are very apt to forget their duty in their Office, eſpecially thoſe that are great and honorable in the World, and that have great parts; but to theſe Mr.
<hi>Jenkins</hi> will be gentle, but as for the other, they are Michanicks; but how muſt he behave himſelf to them? ſurely, as unto the other, gentle to all men, I conceive, as well the weak and obſtinate, as others, abounding in meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards all: And all the thanks I had for my paines in teaching a man the right way, it was to be called unmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fellow: Surely if Mr.
<hi>Jenkins</hi> would ſet the ſaddle upon the right horſe, he ſhould have called the Apoſtles unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly, for that was his word: But Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> taketh it in diſdain to be told his duty from a mean one, though the Meſſage be from the Lord, if the Perſon be not exalted; he will have more of it, forgetting that place, 1 <hi>Tim. 5. 21. I charge thee before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and his elect Angels, that thou obſerve theſe things without preferring one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another, doing nothing by partiallitie:</hi> This Scripture ſhould make Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> tremble at the reading thereof, or elſe he thinketh it not to be the Word of God, or that he is ſo high, it cannot reach him; And that the Injunction of God,
<hi>prefer not one before another,</hi> and <hi>do nothing by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie,</hi> nothing concernes him; But Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſaith, I am above you, I have my fat and my Fleece by ſuch and ſuch, and by them cometh in my gaine; therefore I muſt make a difference, but ſaith the Apoſtle, If you do, look to it, for though you may be corrupted with bribes, yet there are faithfull Judges that will not wink at ſuch things, <hi>Fitus 1. 9. Holding faſt the faithful Word, as he hath been taught,</hi> to what end, <hi>that he may be able by ſound Doctrine both to exhort and to convince gain-ſayers;</hi> the Apoſtle doth not ſay, the rich or poor, but all gain-ſayers, as well of the Laicks, as the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, according to Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> expreſſion; Many Scriptures might be added; but I think this hath ſufficiently cleared the point, that it is the duty of a Miniſter to give ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166061:8"/> to the meaneſt of his Brethren, as to thoſe that are the greateſt.</p>
            <p>Now we ſhall come to examine the ſecond branch of this Reaſon, which is, if it be any thing, it muſt be his humane Learning, and acquired parts which we ſhall now ſpeak to:</p>
            <p>If we finde it to be any where mentioned as a gift, yet we ſhall not find it to be a thing, that thereby they ſhould exalt themſelves above their Brethren. But if Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſaith, This is that which putteth ſo great and vaſt a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and others; whether herein he pleads not like the <hi>Jews,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>We have Abraham to our Father, and are you greater then he?</hi> ſo Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> he hath Humane Learning, and you, ſaith he, are illiterate. But the Word teacheth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. <hi>Phil. 2, 3. Let each eſteem another above himſelf.</hi> Joh. 5. 44. the Apoſtle there ſaith upon the like occaſion as this, of Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> he that would be greater then his Brethren, Chriſt ſaith,
<hi>Let him be your Miniſter, and he that will be chief, let him be ſervant to all: he that abaſeth himſelf ſhall be exalted;</hi> not the proud man, for the Lord looketh upon the proud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off; And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>I Preach not my ſelf, but Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, and my ſelf your ſervant for Jeſus ſake,</hi> 2 Cor. 4, 5. But Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> hath not found this way out, <hi>to become a fool that he may be wiſe;</hi> but rather, his notionall &amp; Human know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge doth puff him up: Let Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and all of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, conſider theſe places of Scripture; The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Though I ſpeak with the tongues of men,</hi> &amp;c. and though eloquent, who through their high flown ſtraines allure the affections of many towards them; And though it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to ſpeak with the tongue of an Angel, <hi>and want Love,</hi> they are <hi>but as ſounding Braſſ, or a tinckling Cymbal:</hi> yea, though a man hath the gift of Propheſie, and underſtands all My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries and Knowledge, which is one ſtep higher then Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> hath gone, yet this is nothing: Doth the Apoſtle make nothing of all this? What reaſon then is there, Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſhould ſet ſo high a value, and boaſt ſo much of his fragments, which, as he ſaith, he ſpent ſo much time as twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166061:8"/> yeers agoe, he had ſtudied Logick, the ſame Apoſtle an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth him again, and ſaith, <hi>If any might have confidence the Fleſh, and hath any thing to boaſt of, I more,</hi> and reck oneth up his Priviledges (jewels they would have been in Mr.
<hi>Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> eyes:) but what is the concluſion of all? <hi>what things were gain I accounted loſſe, and dung, that I might win Chriſt.</hi> So that Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> commeth ſhort in this, to make his Argument good, his ſtrength of parts, and great quallifications ſhould rather be an Argument or reaſon for him to maintain what he ſpake then, or the contrary: there are many of thoſe whom he challenged that for naturall, and acquired Parts, under ſavour come not behinde Mr. <hi>Jenkins.</hi> But by this time, I hope thoſe that have not ſacrifiſed their underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon the Altar of Affection, ſee clearly the invaliditie of this Reaſon.</p>
            <p>2. Another Reaſon why he would not diſpute, was; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knew not whether he ſhould convince the gain-ſayer.</p>
            <p>3. Becauſe Diſputes are the occaſion of ſtriſe: Both which are of ſo little weight and concernment, they are hardly worth ſpeaking to, it being but ſpending time to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, we never find Chriſt nor his Apoſtles deny to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Doctrine concerning Fundamentals upon Maſter <hi>Jenkins</hi> accompt (who were as wiſe as he) which is becauſe they knew not the effect; As for Chriſt, he preached and Diſputed daily with the <hi>Jews, Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Sinners, though he met with great contradiction of ſinners: And we find many were convinced at the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and by the Diſputations of the Apoſtles; As for Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Acts. 9. 29. Acts 17. 17. Acts 18. 19. Paul</hi> Diſputed two yeers in the School of one <hi>Tir annus;</hi> It is not to be thought by any, who have not loſt their Wits, or elſe mad with their Witts, that all were convinced by
<hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Miniſters are commanded to convince gain-ſayers. <hi>Titus</hi> 1. 9. I hope that Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> doth not think;</p>
            <p>Firſt, That gain-ſayers are bound to be convinced by his Arguments.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:166061:9"/>Secondly, That men ſhould imagine that he or any of his coat were unerring, and could not miſtake.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Neither do I think, that though a brother be unſatisfied in what is held forth as a truth, that it is fitting for him that aſſerts any thing for truth, and becauſe another will not conſent thereto, to run with open mouth upon him, and threaten with menaces to take away his life.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That though they act according to the word of truth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1, 2. and do rightly divide the Word of Truth, yet are Miniſters to give (or endeavour to give) ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to gain-ſayers, and to vindicate the truth: And ſo <hi>Apollas</hi> mightily convinced the Jews, and that publikely; ſo that it may clearly appear, That
<list>
                  <item>1. The Apoſtles did diſpute:</item>
                  <item>2. That this Diſpute was publike.</item>
                  <item>3. That the rule by which they proceeded was the word.</item>
                  <item>4. And fourthly you ſee that their undertaking was not in vain.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore in vain doth Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> pleaſe himſelfe with this vain and frivolous excuſe. We find it was matter of reproof for <hi>Jobs</hi> three friends, in that they ſuffered him to juſtifie himſelf, and did not convince him of the evill thereof, but we find it to be a duty enjoyned, and therefore the contrary a very weak plea for him who is aloft, and ſo far exceeds others; but precepts and examples are not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for Mr. <hi>Jenkins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his third reaſon it is included in the ſecond, where there is not conviction, there will be gainſaying and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction. But there are ſome who are not of Mr. <hi>Ienkins</hi> and Mr. <hi>Vicars</hi> frame and temper of ſpirit, which are more noble, like the
<hi>Bereans,</hi> who will ſearch the Scriptures, and ſee what is held forth, for truth doth agree with the Word of Truth, which is the reaſon, I fear, Mr. <hi>Ienkins</hi> declines an ingagement, leaſt thereby he may pull diſhonour on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and appear to be (in truth) that which he would not be accounted to be, which is, an enemy to the Word of truth, but he will ſacrifice life, rather then loſe repute in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166061:9"/> world; which reſolution I eſteem not right, but it is his <hi>Diana,</hi> his Goddeſs: And becauſe of janglings; yet he was pleaſed to ſay, the Goſpel damned ten times more then it ſaved; And Mr. <hi>Ienkins</hi> might as properly have ſaid, If what he held was truth, that the Goſpel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought not to be Preached: But perhaps Maſter
<hi>Jenkins</hi> will ſay, I get my living by preaching, but I may be a loſer by diſputing; by preaching cometh in my Tythes and Offerings; But to me it ſeemeth but juſt, that the
<hi>Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> ſhould as well diſpute as preach, for by his own argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, preaching doth occaſion ſtumbling; and indeed, the more for ſuch as he, becauſe they muſt ſay what they pleaſe, but give no account thereof, and his counterfeit go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for currant Coin, as though ſeaven times purified in the fire, when as if it might be tried, the fiery tryal would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it, and nothing remain extant but the ſhame of ſuch aſſertions; But the truth is, the generality of people are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take all upon earneſt in matters of the greateſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and concernment, and to take all upon truſt to follow a blind guide, though they fall into the ditch with him; but there would be no more janglings in diſputes then in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, were the ſpirits of men but moderate, and could they prove their doctrines by the rule.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Ienkins</hi> may ſay, though I have no Scripture, yet I have this for my argument, that which the Apoſtle ſaith to <hi>Timothy, 2 Tim.</hi> 2. 14. That he was not to ſtrive about words to no purpoſe: And ſo in another place, where we are admoniſhed to ſhun profane and vain bablings, for they will increaſe to more ungodlineſs, &amp;c. of whom is
<hi>Hyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> who concerning the truth have erred; to this I anſwer;
<list>
                  <item>1. That janglings and diſputings are forbidden, is not denied.</item>
                  <item>2. Such diſputes as increaſe ungodlineſs and ſubvert the hearers, that is forbidden, it is not denied.</item>
                  <item>And 3. it is not denied, that diſputes ought to be ſhuned between profane &amp; wicked perſons that deny plain truths.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:166061:10"/>But here is nothing ſpoken but that fundamentall and neceſſary truths to be ſatisfied, ought to be diſputed of, elſe it condemneth the Apoſtles own example and practiſe, for they did do the ſame thing, and exorted to the duty, and yet I preſume none will deny but that they did adminiſter jangling; but that all diſputes ought to be ſhunned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome ought, which tend to vain jangling, it ſeemeth to be an abſurd concluſion. Much more might be ſaid to this purpoſe, but I think enough hath been ſaid in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Mr. <hi>Ienkins</hi> three great Reaſons, to take off the edge of them, that they may make no entrance in the mindes of any men, or cauſe them to think that ſuch a ſlight account of Mr.
<hi>Jenkins</hi> faith will give him a full diſcharge from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which is his duty.</p>
            <p>Now upon the hearing of theſe Reaſons, I told him, they were too light to bear this great weight upon; and that it ſtill did appear to be his duty both from expreſs commands, and example, and if he would not perform it with reſpect to his challenge, yet I deſired him, that he would do it to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge his duty, and to clear the truth, and convince gain-ſayers: for other wiſe, mens mouthes might be juſtly open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt him to ſay that he had declined to make good that which he delivered for a truth; but he regarded me not, then I told him, that if this was his reſolution, I muſt deal plainly with him; if this be all the ſatisfaction we ſhould have, he muſt expect to hear of it in publique, or to meet with publique oppoſition: do what you pleaſe, ſaith he; ſo after a little while he was to ſpeak in publike, and I was there, where he delivered ſome impertinencies, and ſuch things as he did formerly gain-ſay; yea, and at the ſame time alſo, take a taſte of one or two of them; firſt Mr.
<hi>Jenkins</hi> was ſpeaking of Chriſt to be the onely foundation of our Faith, and that Scriptures did manifeſt or ſhew us this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and ſo in his <hi>Biſey Biſhop;</hi> and yet in the <hi>Blinde Guide</hi> grants, there was a time when the Scriptures were not a foundation, nor yet ſo much as a manifeſter of the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith [<hi>Blind Guide.</hi> p. 46, 17.] but it was manifeſted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166061:10"/> by Dreames, Viſions and audible voices, &amp;c. ſo he would have the Scriptures a foundation of truth, and a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſter of the foundation alſo, But I would faine learn of him whether the thing ſhewing, and the thing ſhewed be all one.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſpeaking further concerning this foundation, the ſtrength and largeneſſe of it ſhewed that the reaſon why ſo few are built upon it, is not becauſe it is not ſtrong and large enough for them to build upon, but becauſe men are not willing to build thereon; ſo the reaſon according to Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> Confeſſion, why men build not upon the foundation, is not becauſe they may not, or cannot, but becauſe they will not, and yet in his <hi>Blind Guide,</hi> pag. 80. he ſaith, God deals with mens wills as he will, and when he will, and ſo, like a blind man, ſtrikes at a venture; but we do not much wonder he and all men of his perſwaſion are ſo accuſtomed to it; but more of this in due time.</p>
            <p>After Mr. <hi>Jenkin,</hi> had done all, I began to ſpeak, and as ſoon as ever I began to ſpeak, the <hi>Hireling</hi> fled, not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a word, and his ſheep, like ravening Wolves, or Bulls of <hi>Baſon,</hi> compaſſed me round about, as fierce as Lions, with high indignation; Some crying, Stone him, others, To <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> with him; others, Hang him (before they had judged him) others cryed, To the Devil with him, the Devil pick his beanes; if theſe are not the language of ill tongu'd men, I know not where we ſhall find them: Surely, Mr.
<hi>Jenkins</hi> need not go far to be in the Suburbs of Hell, for according to his own deſcription of the place, it is his own Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he, as a builder in Gods houſe, hath beaten the Ayre: ſurely the ſtones wil be no ornament to it: doubtleſs Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> and his Brethren might have ſaved that labour, as at their own coſt, to ſend out an Army conſiſting of Twenty Generalls, againſt a ſmall company of deſpiſed poor Lay-men: for Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> hath found a new way, ſeeing the other fayled; when they came to pitch a field, either they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> weak, or both, and what
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166061:11"/> they could not do with the ſword of the ſpirit, they can and will with the arm of fleſh, but indeed they might have ſaved that labour alſo, for their chief General quit his ground immediately, however his ſouldiers, to ſhew their valour, after he was fled, would guard the Pulpit, and that they did moſt valiantly, ye ſo gallantly, that I think can hardly be parralell's among profeſſed Chriſtians in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; (to Mr <hi>Fenkins</hi> future praiſe be it:) Well, the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit being thus ſtoutly guarded, there was no making the leaſt attempt thereon, but now being got on the other ſide the hedge, I may make bold to ſpeak (what formerly I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) to the Souldiers and General, which is this; I had thought Mr. <hi>Fenkins</hi> had born greater love to God and his Truth, and had been a greater benefacter to the World, then to preach another Sermon before he had proved his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to be true, when ſo deeply queſtion'd and judged to be an errour, this ſurely would have ſorely hurt Mr. <hi>Fenkins</hi> and his tender lambs to have heard; all my deſigne, the Lord knows, and my conſcience beares me witneſs, was, that the truth might appear, and be more inquired into, that men may not take darkneſs for a Viſion; and ſeeing they count themſelves unworthy of knowing the minde of God, we ſhall the better disſcharge our duty; but as for Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> in as much as he was pleaſed to lay down an Argument, by which he would prove his Doctrine, and defend it againſt all the world; remember <hi>Capernaum</hi> (Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi>) thoſe things were written for our inſtruction: alas, what is it for me to attempt that which the whole world is counted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, the proud <hi>Leviathan,</hi> when ſmitten with a dart, muſt make to the ſands, and <hi>Capernaum</hi> muſt come down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, though Mr. <hi>Ienkins</hi> in fancy be ſo high, yet being he hath ſo ſoarly ſtumbled, a weak man may keep him down, though I confeſs my ſelf much inferiour to many, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take ſuch a buſineſs, yet my heart is good, and my Cauſe better, and therefore I ſhall leave the ſucceſs to him that beſt knows both; Mr. <hi>Ienkins</hi> Argument was this; That Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that contradicts that Scripture which ſaith, <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166061:11"/> ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Mark. 16. 16. is an erronious Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>But that opinion which holdeth a poſſibility of loſing the Savour of Chriſt, or falling from faith contradicts that Scripture, <hi>ergo</hi> Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> here, by believing in the major propoſition, muſt mean the firſt act of faith, and by faith in the ſecond propoſition, or <hi>minor,</hi> he muſt mean the ſame thing, <hi>viz.</hi> the firſt act of faith, or elſe he ſaith nothing; and if his meaning be ſo, I deny his <hi>minor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſay that though it be poſſible for a man to loſe the Savour of Chriſt, yet it will not contradict that Scripture; but we ſhall wave that, and make a little ſearch into the Text upon which Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> argument is grounded, where there is a promiſe, and a threatning, and both ſeem abſolute life upon the firſt act of believing, and death unto thoſe to whom it is tendred, and do not believe: Now if Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> will underſtand the former part of the vefſe, the promiſe to be abſolute, by the ſame reaſon muſt he underſtand the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part, wherein the <hi>threaten</hi> is contained to be abſolute al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; for there is no reaſon to be given from the words to the contrary; but if I can firſt prove, that both the
<hi>promiſe</hi> and <hi>threatning</hi> here, are conditional. 2 That there hath been thoſe that have loſt the ſavour of Chriſt, then I think this Argument will be layed in the duſt, and diſcharged from this hard duty it is put upon; As for the firſt, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more evident in the Scripture that I know of, to wit, that ſuch promiſes are conditional, and though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them ſeem to be abſolute, yet they are not ſo to be underſtood, and if this promiſe in the Text ſhould be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, <hi>viz.</hi> That men upon the firſt act of believing ſhould be unqueſtionably aſſured of eternal glory, however they behave themſelves afterwards, and that no ſin or ſinnes whatſoever ſhould be able to ſeparate God and them. See how it would preſent God unlike to himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> after he hath given them ſuch an aſſurance by promiſe abſolute, to require conditions of them, and telling of them, that they ſhall not be ſaved, unleſs they hold out unto the end, <hi>Eſay</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:166061:12"/> 59. 2. as though God ſhould ſpeak at ſuch a rate, how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent to an unchangeable God appears to be, <hi>viz.</hi> To ſay, You that truly beleeve in my Son, and have been once made partakers of my holy Spirit, and are fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded according to my Will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand given unto you, which you<note place="margin">See <hi>Mr.</hi> Goodwin's Redem. redeem.
<hi>p. 318.</hi>
               </note> have in you from me, which you cannot poſſibly, no, not by the moſt horrid ſins, or abominable practiſes, that you ſhall, or can commit, fall away either totally or finally; you know, it is impoſſible you ſhould die in your ſins, you that know, and are aſſured, I will lay an irreſiſtable hand of grace on you, and worke perſeverance in you, and ſo you ſhall be out of the reach of condemnation; therefore there remains nothing for you, but onely giving of thanks; and do you what you will, in the mean time, you know I will neceſſitate you to that alſo, and yet I earneſtly charge, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh and beſeech you, that you take heed to your ſelves, that ye continue in the faith, and that there be not in you at any time an evill heart of unbelief in departing from the living God, and that ye fall not from your own ſtedfaſtneſs; yea, I declare and profeſs unto you, that if you do, my ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in you, and if you denie me, I will denie you; and if you be overcome again of the luſts of the fleſh and the World, being intangled here in your ſins, your latter end ſhall be worſe then your beginning; and if you turn away, all your righteouſneſs ſhall not be remembred, but you ſhall die in your ſins, and ſuffer the eternall ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of hell fire; on the other hand, If you <hi>continue unto the end,</hi> my Promiſe is, <hi>you ſhall be ſaved; be thou faithfull unto death, and I will give thee a Crowne of life;</hi> therefore <hi>ſtrive to enter in at the ſtraight gate, labour for the meat that periſheth not; watch ye, ſtand faſt in the faith, quit your ſelves like men, be ſtrong; ye are made partakers of Chriſt if ye hold the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your confidence ſtedfaſt unto the end; and be not ſlothfull, but followers of them, who through faith and patience have inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited the Promiſes:</hi> Surely, were not Mr. <hi>Ienkins</hi> mightily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:166061:12"/> againſt the light of this truth, he cannot thuſe but ſee a great deal of difference between thoſe exortations, threathings and later promiſes, and thoſe declarations, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications and former promiſes, and cannot chuſe, if he holds thoſe former comes from God, the later muſt be from ſome body elſe; or elſe if the later come from God, the former from ſome body elſe; or if they came all from God, then thoſe that ſeem abſolute, are yet conditional; or elſe thoſe that are conditionall, are nothing. Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> would ſurely be rendred no wiſe man, in caſe he ſhould make his child heir of his eſtate, and actually inveſt him in it, and give him the greateſt ſecurity as poſſibly he can for one ſingle act that hath well pleaſed him, and he ſo farre binds himſelf to perform it, as it is now claimed as a proper right, both abſolutely and actually, and then Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſhould come to his child, and tell him there is ſomething more to be done, and he muſt do it diligently, and continue in doing of it as long as he lives, or elſe he ſhall loſe that as he hath ſolemnly &amp; abſolutely given him without conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; would not he render himſelf rediculus? and yet at ſuch a rate, would he make God to ſpeak and act; but now as this Scripture ſeems to be abſolute, ſo we ſhall give you a taſte of Scriptures that ſeem to be abſolute (as they are all in God <hi>yea and Amen</hi>) but to us is the condition in the event, or thing determined upon ſuch terms, as is ſuſpended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the condition included in the detirmination, as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, it cannot be denied, but God had determined to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<hi>Nineveh</hi> within Fourty dayes after, warned by <hi>Jonahs</hi> preaching unto them,
<hi>Jonah</hi> 3. 10. for ſurely, if he had not purpoſed or decreed it, he would never have ſent his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to preach it in his Name; but becauſe the purpoſe and determination of God was conditionall, it implyes onely his purpoſe of inflicting this puniſhment determined upon them, in caſe they had not humbled themſelves in ſuch a time limited, therefore this decree, purpoſe, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of God, though it ſeems to be abſolute, yet it is not ſo to be underſtood, but conditionall; ſo likewiſe in the caſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:166061:13"/> of <hi>Eli,</hi> 1 Sam. 2. 30. <hi>Wherefore the Lord of Iſrael ſaith, I ſaid indeed,</hi> that is, <hi>I purpoſed or determined, that thy houſe, and the houſe of thy father ſhould walk before me, viz.</hi> in the dignity and office of the Prieſthood for ever; but now the Lord ſaid, Far be it from me, the reaſon is, becauſe, <hi>Him that honoureth me, him will I honour; but they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed.</hi> Here alſo is an abſolute promiſe as one would think, when God ſaid, or determined
<hi>Ely's</hi> houſe ſhould walk before him for ever; there was no condition expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but included as plainly appears in the event: The time would faile to run over all the places that lift up their hand to this truth; namely that the promiſe and threatning of God; I mean of this nature only, take a taſte of them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 17. &amp;c. <hi>Wherefore,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>come ye out from among them, and touch no unclean thing, and I will receive you, and be a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto you, and you ſhall be my ſons and daughters, ſaith the Lord:</hi> And the uſe the Apoſtle makes of this conditionall promiſe, is this, <hi>Having theſe promiſes, dearely beloved, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the face of God:</hi> So likewiſe <hi>Rev. 2. 10. Be thou faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto death, and I will give thee a crown of life,</hi> with <hi>Rom. 11. 22, 23. Matth. 7. 7. Joh. 16. 21. Hebr. 4. 1. 1 Cor. 6. 9, 10. Gal. 5. 21. Joh.</hi> 15. 7. &amp; 10. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. 16. all which ſpeak aloud, that the promiſes and threatnings of God, as in the caſe before ſpecified, are conditional.</p>
            <p>Much more might be ſaid to the clearing of this truth, and making null the Argument; but in my judgement there hath been ſo much ſaid, that were not men prejudiced againſt it with more then ordinary diſaffection, they could not chuſe but ſee a truth in it; yet notwithſtanding I ſhall proceed to the ſecond particular, in order to the clearing of the Queſtion, to wit, to give an inſtance or two of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that have had the ſavour of Chriſt, and yet have loſt it: We ſhall begin with <hi>Hymeneus, Philetus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> where
<hi>Paul</hi> exhorts <hi>Timothy</hi> to keep that as others had loſt, to wit, faith and a good conſcience, of whom is <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letus;</hi> and ſo 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 17. and their words will eat as doth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:166061:13"/> a canker, of whom is <hi>Hymeneus</hi> &amp; <hi>Alexander,</hi> who have erred<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 19, 20.</note> from the truth, ſaying, The reſurrection is paſt already, and overthrow the faith of ſome men: From the former of theſe two, it is evident, that <hi>Hymenius</hi> &amp; <hi>Alexander</hi> had faith, and that
<hi>ſaving</hi> alſo, or ſuch a faith as would or did capaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate them for ſalvation; the reaſon is, The Apoſtle exhorts him to hold the ſame, and no other than that which they had put away, and then, if that they had was not ſound, the Apoſtle exhorts them to hold or keep that which would ſtand them in no ſtead: No, it would then have been ſuch a faith as would have been a ſnare unto them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe it was accompanied with a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, a man can never be ſaid to have a good Conſcience unleſs he have ſaving faith, becauſe ſo long as he is in a ſtate of unregeneracie and unbelief, his Conſcience ſtands accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of him, and ſo long <hi>not good;</hi> a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> is more clearly amplified in the fifth verſe of this Chapter, the end of the <hi>command</hi> is <hi>Charity</hi> out of a pure heart, and a <hi>good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and faith unfained; and he that hath a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, muſt needs have a pure heart, they are ſo linked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and all being the end of the Law, that it is impoſſible to have the one, and want the other; So the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, [1 Pet. 3. 15, 16.] Sanctifie the Lord in your hearts, and be ready to give an anſwer to every one that ſhall ask, a reaſon of the hope that is in you, with meekneſs and fear, having a good conſcience,</hi> &amp;c. a little after he ſums up the end, or placeth the ſum or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of true Chriſtianity in a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> though the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are not excluded, which ſhews that for a man to have a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> is to be eminently in the favour of God, and that a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> proceedeth from unfaigned faith; <hi>See</hi> 1 Tim. 3. 9. Hebr.
9, 14. and 10. 22. compared to the former, doth clearly evince this to be a truth.</p>
            <p>Neither is that much conſiderable which ſome would create to excuſe themſelves in conceiting the contrary, to wit, That by faith here, is meant the Doctrine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; but whether it be the Doctrine of the Goſpel, or the act of faith, it will amount to one and the ſame, if a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:166061:14"/> man doth receive or hold the Doctrine of the Goſpel with a good conſcience, it muſt be with a pure heart; and neither of theſe can be without faith, which is the ground-work of all; ſo they that notionize this to relieve them, will take darkneſs for a viſion; but if it be ſaid, the Apoſtle could not tell what men were, they knew not the hearts of men; and ſo the men that made ſhip-wrack of faith might not have ſuch a good conſcience as is pleaded for; but let thoſe men of this perſwaſion conſider whether the Apoſtle ſpake theſe words as a man, or whether it was not God in the man; if the Apoſtle had no better inſight in the buſineſs, we have little ground to believe, that the holding that he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts us to, will do us any great good, in caſe we ſhould hold it; and ſo they would make God ſpeak like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: there is nothing can rationally be concluded by any to refute this ſenſe contended for, but the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the nature of a good conſcience will repeal it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore very evident it is, that thoſe men that had faith and a good conſcience, had the Savour of Chriſt, and that in an eminent manner. We ſhall mention two more inſtances; we ſhall briefly run over them, that is <hi>David</hi> and his ſon <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> as for
<hi>David,</hi> I think it is no mans Queſtion, whether he had not the ſavour of Chriſt, and was a true and reall Saint before the committing of thoſe two horrid ſinnes of murther and adultery; for he had this ſignall teſtimony, of being a man after Gods own heart, which was given unto him by God himſelf, before he had committed thoſe two ſins, as appears, 1
<hi>King.</hi> 14. 8. with <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 22. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 20. this I think no man denieth; but the Quaere is, whether he remained truly godly under the guilt, ſince from the time of his committing of them to the time of his repentance; they do not ſtick to affirm it, but I muſt of neceſſity deny it, and the reaſon is, becauſe he that commits murther and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery againſt the light of conſcience, and with much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, and remaines under the guilt of theſe ſins with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance, is not a man that is truely godly, or that hath the Savour of Chriſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:166061:14"/>But <hi>David</hi> is ſuch a one, <hi>ergo</hi> as for the firſt Propoſition it doth not need much proof; for he that ſhall act, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remorſe of conſcience commit that as is expreſly againſt the command of God, cannot be a man in the doing of that in the fear of God, or love of God, becauſe of their want of obeying of God; but we ſhall a little illuſtrate it with a ſecond, thus, he that is truly godly, and hath the Savour of Chriſt in him, hath by the gracious promiſe of God a right unto the Kingdome of glory; this I think is not denied by any; therefore he that commits murther and adultery hath no right to the Kingdome of glory, during his impenitency under the guilt of theſe ſins; <hi>ergo,</hi> for the confirmation of this, we ſhall give an expreſs Text of Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9, 10. No whoremongers, and mutherers, nor adulterers, &amp;c. ſhall enter into the Kingdome of God; and they that do ſuch things, ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of God, <hi>Gal. 5. 21. Epheſ.</hi> 5. 5, 6. ſo that <hi>David</hi> while he remained impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, under the committing of theſe two abominations, was a ſubject of death, on whom the wrath of God ſhould abide for ever; and he was, according to Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, in the ſuburbs of hell; thoſe things that are viſibly objected againſt, it being the traditions of men onely, and the Scriptures ſo clear againſt it, I ſhall not trouble the Reader with them. Another inſtance we have in <hi>Salomon</hi> alſo, that he, before his falling in adultery, and other miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, was a true believer, and one that had the Savour of Chriſt, is manifeſt; and is not, as I know, denied by any; for <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Salomon,</hi> ſaith, That among many Nations there was no King like unto him; for he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of his God,
<hi>Nohe.</hi> 13. 6. but their confeſſion ſaveth a proof of that; and that he alſo ſinned at an eminent rate, is that alſo they do not deny: A Catalogue of his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is reckoned up by God himſelf in 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 1, 2, 3. his heart was not perfect with the Lord God, as was the heart of his father <hi>David;</hi> that he did that which was evil in the ſight of the Lord; that the Lord was angry with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his heart was turned from the Lord God of Iſrael; and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:166061:15"/> this his father warn'd him of before his death, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 9. therefore evident it is <hi>Salomon</hi> loſt the ſavour of Chriſt: Much more migh be ſaid to this controverſie, but ſeeing Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> lieth bound to defend his Doctrine, I am onely to give anſwer to what is alledged by way of proof, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe much, and that with abundance of light, might be ſhewed to confirm that Doctrin that pleads againſt his; and ſurely if I ſhould deliver any thing for the mind of God in a publik Congregation, or any where elſe, if I would not ſtand to defend it againſt gainſayers, when ſo deeply queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned; I ſhould be aſhamed to appear to ſpeak in the Name of God any more, much more to take Tythes and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to look after Tyth Mint and Aniſe, and neglect one great part of the Miniſtery, ſeeing what Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> hath yet brought to prove his Doctrine, is found too ſcant for that ſervice, but is clearly detected and diſcharged from, it lieth upon him as he wil anſwer the neglecting of his making ful proof of his Miniſtery, to ſhew himſelf one that need not be aſhamed, but rightly dividing the word truth, or in truth.</p>
            <p>Therefore let it be ſeriouſly minded by all Rationall and underſtanding Chriſtians;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether thoſe that profeſs themſelves to be Miniſters of the Goſpel, and yet refuſe to prove and defend their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (when queſtion'd) are indeed Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, Conſidering the Apoſtle in giving Rules and Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to <hi>Titus</hi> in and about ordaining of Miniſters or Elders, 1 <hi>Tet.</hi> 9. preſcribe how he ſhould make choice of ſuch quallif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſons as ſhould be able &amp; willing both to exhort and convince gainſayers therefore whether thoſe that do not anſwer thoſe ends of Miniſters, are not pretended Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters onely, or otherwiſe very weak and unorthy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether thoſe Perſons that thus pretend to be Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds of the flock of Chriſt, and yet neglect thoſe things that are Eſſentially neceſſary to the keeping the Flock in green Paſtures, and alſo to keep the Wolf from them, are not ſuch as creep in at a back door, and ſo appear to be no leſs then <hi>Hyrelings,</hi> taking but little care of the Flock, gaping more
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:166061:15"/> after the fleece, to fether their own neſts, then after the ſheep, to lead them in freſh Paſtures, more for filthy lucre, then of a ready minde?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether it be not probable that ſuch Sheepherds, yea, whither it be not apparent that they do grow ſo careleſs of the Flock (that when the Wolf cometh, or when ſome ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing profit is like to redowne to them in other places) flee from them; and like bad and covetous ſervants, that would ſerve two Maſters, render themſelves deſpiſers of God, and his ſervice?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether when the chief Shepherd ſhall appear, to call the inferior ſhepherds to an Account, it will not go hard with the <hi>Hireling,</hi> when the Shepherd will appear that will judge infallibly indeed; then woe to lazy Lozzells that creep in at the back-door, when He ſhall come to Crown faithfull Shepherds with a Crown of glory, the <hi>Hyreling's</hi> reward will not be according to this truth, <hi>of well done good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Let it alſo be conſidered, whether ſuch Shepherds that take no more care for their flocks, and of making full proof of their faithfulneſs in the Miniſtry, ought to be Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced by Authoritie in their granting of what mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance they defire, and that they ſhould take ſo much care for their body, that will take no more care (according to their duty and profeſſion) for precious ſouls of men?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether Shepherds are not bound to feed the flock, and alſo to lead them in green paſtures, and that with much care and faithfulneſs, though the ſheep do not every yeer caſt their coat, conſidering the former is injoyned, though the latter remain unperform'd?</p>
            <div type="queries">
               <p>I Had thought here to have ended, having as I humbly conceive, given a full anſwer to Mr.
<hi>Jenkin's</hi> Argument, yet being deſirous to do ſome thing which I conceive may give ſome light to the Controvercy; I ſhall humbly <hi>Quere.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="query">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:166061:16"/>
                  <head>QUERE I.</head>
                  <p>WHether the Word of God, which is pretended to hold forth an <hi>impoſſibilitie of true Beleevers declyning to death,</hi> doth not teach, will all, that it is <hi>poſſible</hi> for ſuch Perſons, <hi>Viz.</hi> Beleevers, to commit ſuch ſins, as againſt the committers where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of God pronounceth Eternal death, as in <hi>Matth. 21. 43. Mark 10. 15. Rom. 14. 17. 1 Cor.
6. 9, 10, 11. Gal. 5. 29.</hi> Epheſ. 5. 5. and divers other places, it appeareth, and ſo it be not rendred inconſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent with it ſelf, by ſuch an opinion?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="query">
                  <head>QUERE II.</head>
                  <p>Whether ſuch Perſons as fall totally from the grace and love of God, may not poſſibly fall finally alſo, conſidering that there is no promiſe from God, that ſuch Perſons ſhall neceſſarily and irreſiſtably be brought back again by repentance?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="query">
                  <head>QUERE III.</head>
                  <p>Whether that Doctrin that teacheth an <hi>utter impoſſibilitie of the Saints falling away from the love of God</hi> be not a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that renders God a reſpecter of Perſons, and a God that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth, loveth and delighteth in ſuch as are by the Scripture term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed children of
<hi>Belial,</hi> and <hi>workers of iniquitie,</hi> contrary to <hi>2 Sam. 2. 14. 2 Cor. 19. 7. Acts. 10. 34. Job. 37. 24. Eph. 6. 4. 1 Pet. 17. Rom. 2. 11. Col. 3. 25.</hi> with many others?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="query">
                  <head>QUERE. IIII.</head>
                  <p>Whether Infants, in their ſtate of Infancy (according to the common notion of Election) are not in a ſtate of grace, and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently beloved of God? and whether when they come to Act, they fall not from that ſtate, and become children of wrath as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="query">
                  <head>QUERE V.</head>
                  <p>Whether that Doctrine which teacheth an <hi>Impoſſibilitie of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers falling finally out of the love of God,</hi> that commit ſuch things (as God pronounceth them unmeet ſubjects for his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) doth not give God the lye, who ſaith, They that commit ſuch things ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God? <hi>1 Cor. 6. 9. Joh. 15. 6. 10. 1 Sam. 2. 30. Gen. 4. 7.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="query">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:166061:16"/>
                  <head>QUERE VI.</head>
                  <p>Whether the ſaid Doctrine doth not make uſeleſs all thoſe exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and perſwaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ons, that God applies himſelf in unto Beleevers, to <hi>watch and Pray continually, to ſtand faſt in the faith,</hi> to quit themſelves like men, <hi>to look to themſelves, leaſt they looſe</hi> the thing they have gained, <hi>to be faithful unto death, and you are made partakers of Chriſt, if you hold the beginning of your Confidence or faith ſtedfaſt unto the end;</hi> and take heed leaſt there be found in any of you an evil heart of unbelief in departing from the living God, with a multitude of like nature?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="query">
                  <head>QUERE VII.</head>
                  <p>Whether the ſaid Doctrine which ſuppoſeth the ſaid <hi>Impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</hi> doth not alſo make void, render uſeleſs the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, at leaſt one main branch thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo far as it is furniſhed by God, and appointed for the perſeverance of the Saints, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming them in the faith?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="query">
                  <head>QUERE. VIII.</head>
                  <p>Whether the ſaid opinion of an <hi>abſolute impoſſibilitie of the Saints falling away finally,</hi> doth not repreſent the beſt, wiſeſt and bolieſt of men, and that when they were moſt effectually aſſiſted, and infallibly guided by the holy Ghoſt, to ſpeak Nonſcenſe, as when the Propbet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaith, <hi>If the righteous man forſaketh his righteouſneſs, he ſhall die:</hi> If we ſay, it is impoſſible for him ſo to
<hi>forſake</hi> it as to die; and whereas the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I beat down my body, and keep it in ſubjection, leaſt when I have preached to others, I my ſelf ſhould become a caſt-a-way,</hi> or a reprobate; whether I ſay, to ſuppoſe a Saint cannot become a
<hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate,</hi> be not to render the ſaying weak, and rediculous, and to make him to ſpeak after this Ayrie light manner, <hi>I beat down my body, and keep it in ſubjection, leaſt when I have Preached to others, I my ſelf ſhould become (that which it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ever for me to be)</hi> viz. <hi>a eaſt-away</hi> or <hi>reprobate?</hi> Yea,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="query">
                  <head>QUERE IX.</head>
                  <p>Whether the ſaid opinion oppoſed, doth not make God himſelf
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:166061:17"/> alſo to ſpeak at ſuch a rate of weakneſſe and contradictions, in ſuppoſing impoſſibilities, as hath been laid down?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="query">
                  <head>QUERE X.</head>
                  <p>Whether the ſaid opinion hath not a very naturall and ſtrong tendency in it to ſtrengthen the hands of wicked men, to proceed in wicked actions, and to weaken the reſolutions of holy men, fearing the Lord in wayes of exactneſs in walking, and carefulneſs in the ſame, and conſequently to make Profeſſors turn head upon the way of holineſs and righteouſneſs, and to give way to all the will of the old man; therefore let it be conſidered, whether this be a Doctrine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to godlineſs?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>Thus I ſhall conclude, humbly deſiring all men that hope to be partakers of the Saints
<hi>inheritance,</hi> which is <hi>undefiled,</hi> and whereinto no <hi>unclean thing ſhall enter;</hi> Conſider in the feare of the Lord, whether ſuch a Doctrine, as is here oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is like to be from God? and whether there be not great reaſon to queſtion the ſame, and throughly to look into it, that ſo darkneſs be may exſpell'd, and the light of truth break forth, and be imbraced, to the glory of God, and ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of all men.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg. 2. lin. 23. for</hi> the <hi>read</hi> this. p. 3. <hi>l. 30. dele</hi> but onely they.
<hi>p. 6. l 23. for</hi> though I give them not to you in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>read</hi> though he gave them not to me in order.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
